[Music]
okay
so now we come to what I think is in
some sense the the the soul of
RL okay the temporal difference methods
right so I think I think TD is very very
important so I mean you can argue that
RL is all about learning from samples
learning to control Dynamic comp complex
system by just sampling from the system
and so on so forth in which case like
the Montica methods we talked about are
also reinforcement learning methods
right but for
me what is really cool about ARL is the
whole idea of temporal
difference
okay so what do temporal difference
method there are many ways which I can
motivate
this did any of you hear me in sh's
class last
semester you did but you don't count
very in shakti's
class yeah you're there it I didn't even
notice you in the class you kept too
quiet or maybe you didn't show up that
day you did huh ah
okay anyway so that you're only person
so but you don't count you're not taking
the class for credit are you no okay you
don't count but anyway so I I motivated
in a very different way temporal
difference I motivated in a very
different way from a completely
Neuroscience or not even Neuroscience
more like a uh behavioral psychology
point of view okay so now I'll do it
purely from a computational point of
view right so let's start off so what uh
what did we do when we did
uh dynamic
programming right so one way of thinking
about what we did with dynamic
programming you start with some State s
right then you look at all possible
outcomes
right you look at all possible outcomes
from that state right so what is so this
is all possible let's say these are
actions right so all possible actions I
can
take and all possible outcomes from
those
actions right so what does this
correspond to
my my PSA right so Su over a PSA so
that's what this corresponds to and what
does what do this things correspond to
this
much some S Prime P S Prime is given s
comma a right so this is essentially
what I did when I did dynamic
programming right so so every time I did
a backup I took the entire possible
outcome right and I took looked at each
one of
the states here I used the values of the
St and did a backup right I did a backup
so this kind of backups are
[Music]
called Full backups right and it's also
distinguished by the fact that I am
using the values here right this is
called
bootstrapping I did a full backup and I
did that using bootstrapping
okay so next we looked
at multicar method so what we do in mod
methods I started in a
state took some action went to another
state took some other action went to
another state I did this till
I reach a terminal State then I use the
rewards along the entire trajectory and
updated the value of that
state right so what did I do here these
are called sample
backups because I didn't take the full
possible set of outcomes I just sampled
an
outcome okay I just sampled an outcome
and I don't use any bootstrapping so I
don't use the value of this state to
update the value of the state right of
course in the three SE thing we talking
but we did use bootstrapping but now we
are not using any bootstrapping the
plain vanilla thing we don't use
[Music]
any no
bootstrapping
correct so what do you think I can do
next
huh bootstrap and Sample yeah so I can
do sample
[Music]
backups with
bootstrap okay and I'll be
extreme that's
all one sample and I'll boot strap just
like we did here one sample but you went
all the way to the end we no bootstrap
so here what I'll do I'll start from
some State I'll take an action I'll look
at the next outcome and use the value of
the state to update the value of the
state right in a full backup I do all of
this and update here there's no
simulation also involved right I'm just
using all possible outcomes while here
there's a simulation involved here
there's a simulation involved but here
it's only a one step simulation I just
used the value of this state to backup
okay so such methods are called temporal
difference methods
why are they called temporal
difference estimated
other way around use the value at t +
one to get a estimate of the value at
T right so essentially look at the
prediction you make a Time t + 1 you
that for changing the prediction you
made a Time T right so look at the
difference over time so it's is called
temporal difference you look at the
difference in predictions over time you
call this call this a temporal
difference prediction
okay that's a very pictorial motivation
for why you want to do something like
that okay let's do a little bit more
formal thing right so if you think about
uh what we did with Monte Carlo methods
is that I was interested in looking
[Music]
at
that right but at every point of time I
had some sample GT okay I didn't have
the expected value I just had some value
that sample as GT right so if I want to
write this as a stochastic averaging
method right so what will I do I
have so we had is okay let me not put
that it'll confuse people a little bit
so we had uh let not put let me put new
so I want to form a new estimate of V
hat so what will I do I'll take V hat
old
plus some Alpha
times right this will give me we had new
so this is the
classical stochastic averaging rule that
we looked at from very beginning we have
been seeing stochastic averaging rule I
told you that almost everything that
we'll see later will convert it to a
stochastic averaging rule right so this
is a stochastic averaging version
of
what mon Carlo evaluation right this is
mul policy evaluation this is stochastic
averaging version of it right so you can
think of this
as old value okay that
is
Target minus
current okay so the target minus the
current prediction right added to your
old prediction gives me the new
prediction right and this is some form
of
a ER term
right okay so I can I can make
this and this this is what we said was a
stochastic averaging rule right so in
the Bandit case then we showed you this
Alpha should be 1 byn and we can keep a
constant Alpha all of those things we
talked about right so this all of you
are on board with this expression so
this is essentially the incremental
version
of simple Monte Carlo simple Monte Carlo
estimator right without all the other
complications I spoke about today no
important sampling nothing okay I have a
policy F I'm evaluating the policy F
this is the
estimator Target is this the expected
value of GT
right the target is an expected value of
GT but I don't know the
expectation I don't know the expected
value of GT so all I have is
a
sample right one sample of this quantity
of whose expectation I'm taking right so
I plug in that sample here instead of
the target actually we don't have a
sample of have one step no no no I'm
talking about mod here I'm not talking
about this why that's why I kept saying
say this is the incremental version of
simple
MC
okay so everybody on board so this is
simp
MC not t so everybody on board with
that yes no
maybe good so now let us go look at this
target fellow
closely okay so what is the target it's
GT right so what is GT going to look
like
right so we'll do the same trick that we
did earlier
[Music]
correct if I know the True
Value and since I don't know the True
Value I'm going to write this as
now can I plug this into
this if I want to I
mean right so now I can say that
is
right so everybody on board with
that yes no
maybe to notice where the new is where
the old is and where the t is and where
the t+ one is it's important
okay so remember it right so I don't
want you to tell me later that you are
using value at time T to form an estimat
time t +
1 it's very careful you are forming an
estimat time t plus one that's why this
is indicated new initially I wrote VT
and I erased it and wrote new because I
wanted to make the distinction okay so
the value function estimate is new
estimate okay but I'm making it for the
state I encounter time
T okay and I'm using the old value I had
for the state I encountered a Time t +
1 right so this deration clear right so
what we did here very simple essentially
the same trick that we use for deriving
the bman updates right so the same trick
I used here except that I plugged it
into instead of plugging it into the
original return equation I plugged it
into the mon Carlo update right I use
the same trick plugged it into the
Monaro update I get this expression okay
so if you think about it this is exactly
what I wrote here in the
picture right so I'm going to update the
value of this state I'll use the reward
I get plus the value at the
state okay
so a value I mean policy evaluation
algorithm that uses this kind of an
update for finding the value function
okay is called
a TD zero
algorithm right so I mean you should be
able to write a whole algorithm around
this and be able to implement and all
that right so you start off with some uh
arbitrary guess for the value function
you have a fixed policy Pi you start off
with some guess for the value function
then you start generating trajectories
right as you go along the trajectory you
keep updating the value function using
this update so we come to the end of an
episode you go back reset the state but
don't reset the value function okay
reset the stat and
continue okay so that's essentially
what's going to happen
you could have mean all kinds of tricks
you could use you could have an
optimistic initial value right you could
do all kinds of different kinds of
Explorations on top of the basic policy
right if you're going to use exploration
on top of the basic policy what you
should be careful
about
huh my God this is a chapter yeah this a
chapter one question
should you or should you not you update
the policy that falling if you know I'm
we're talking about valuation here I'm
not talking about evaluation here so I'm
not talking about control right in
evaluation you should not but I'm trying
to evaluate a fixed policy if you update
over an exploratory action you're
evaluating a different policy right over
exploratory actions you should not make
any
updates
Okay so that's basically td0 right so we
have done one algorithm now this is the
basic policy evaluation
algorithm right so people understand the
concept of TD what we are doing here
we're looking at things that's one step
away and we are trying to update things
okay so let us
uh see that's what when you're look when
you're doing the uh the depth limited
roll outs right in some sense you are
doing something like
this right so one way of thinking about
depth limited roll outs is that
right when doing depth limited roll
that's what you're doing so I'm counting
the reward until I reach a certain point
in time after that I'm adding the value
function so that's exactly what you're
doing there right so you can think of
this as just one step roll out not even
uh so it's like I just take one step and
immediately use the value
function so that's one way of thinking
about it but I'm doing only one sample
in roll outs I've done that multiple
times but here I'm doing just one
sample we'll come back and explore this
question a little bit later right in the
next chapter we'll explore this question
where we'll explain why the zero is
there okay there's a family of
algorithms called TD Lambda
algorithms where we'll actually look at
this kind of having multiple step uh
rewards and then having the value
function okay so we'll talk about that
next next time yeah why do the update V
of St and not V of
st+ well you didn't ask me that question
when we doing
monlo here it seems more of this no
question no no I'm asking I'm asking you
to think about what we did in the M case
right so we started in some State yes
right we generated an entire trajectory
and we used that to update this value so
I'm instead of generating the entire
trajectory I'm just substituting this GT
with a biased sample but I'm still
considering the return starting from s
St right my question is why don't we do
that because I'm not measuring the
return from St +1 right I could update
the value of st+ 1 but not using this
expression I have to use St +2
here I'm saying so use V of St to get an
estimate of V of s+1 no how then use RT
+1 no no no why am I getting a estimate
of we had of St + 1 from vat of St I'm
saying see V hat of St + 1 if if I don't
have any Loops in my state space V hat
of St + 1 will not even have vat of St
in its
expression the only way V of St St will
enter into the expression for V of St
plus one if you come back to
St right but St is a you know it's a
Time index random variable so you'll
never come back to St
I'm just trying I mean maybe it's not
exactly relevant but I'm thinking of
something like Colman filter where you
do it the other instead
of Colman
filter you trying to predict what the
next state is going to be right so here
I'm not doing that prediction right so
if you want you can write a colon filter
like equation here to predict what the
next state would be what I'm trying to
predict here what I'm trying to learn
here is the the not starting from this
state I'm not trying to predict the next
state it's entirely possible for you to
write expression for St + one in terms
of St but not we hat his + one in terms
of we hat
his does that make
sense no we'll talk we can talk offline
yeah
right yeah
let's talk I I actually had some other
thought we can talk about it later yeah
uh anyway so that's td0 right so any
other questions on
td0 okay good so I'm going to talk a
little bit about some trying to make it
a little bit clearer as to what the
difference between Monte Carlo and TD
methods would give you right so we'll
start off with a very simple data set
right so I'm going to give you
and that's a terminal state after that
right so it's a sequence of states and
rewards that you have observed
let's assume the policy is very dumb
policy okay because I'm doing evaluation
right the policy is fixed I don't have
to worry about the actions so whatever
is the policy right I just observe the
sequence of states and rewards right so
what is the value of
a what is the value of
B if I use mon
Carlo let's say let's say I use first
visit M let's keep things simple I first
visit monlo so what is the value of a
what's the value of
b or let me make things even simpler
let's have no first visit every visit
[Music]
business so what's the value of a
huh it's not not critical for our
example so we'll just keep coming one 4X
3 right what about B
sorry yeah okay I'll make your let's not
have seven anywhere
okay okay so this is essentially a mon
estimate
did I make a mistake
here hey sorry guys I made a mistake in
the number I just cooked up some numbers
and just realize now both Monte Carlo
and TD will give you the same answers so
I need to give you a set of numbers
where Monte Carlo and TD will give you
different
answers
okay um
[Music]
okay
it's
m
correct V of a
is 1 + 2 by 3 so
1 B is 3 by 6 is 1 by
2 okay so what will be the values
estimated by T
essentially what you have to do is you
have to keep updating this rule
repeatedly till you
converge okay I'm not that cruel
okay what you can show which we not true
but what you can show is that TD has
this amazing property that you are
applying that rule incrementally but it
computes the value function by
implicitly constructing
an a Marco
process right so if you think about it
every time I'll go from A to B right so
whenever I update the value of a I use
the value of B so in some sense I'm
implicitly encoding that transition into
my updation so it essentially it look
like something like this so
a go to B and B will go to
a terminal State we can see that with
probability one all of these transitions
will happen right what is the reward for
going from A to
B okay the reward is 2x3 the probability
is one right like what that's expected
reward right I'm just removing so what's
the reward from going from B to the
terminal
state right so
now the value function that the TD
update will converge to is the value
function of a and b in this mdp or in
this markco
chain right so what is the value of B in
chain half that won't change okay here's
the important interesting part what is
the value of a in this Mark of
shap it is the immediate
reward
plus gamma * value of
B right gamma is
one huh
7 by what
six people people accept this right so
what is the value of a is the immediate
reward plus the value of the next state
right so that's the the bman equation so
the immediate reward is 2x3 the value of
the next state turns out to be half in
this case which we already computed
right so 7x 6 so it came to a different
answer than Monte
Carlo right Monte Carlo gave me one and
half TD is giving me 7 by 6
and2 which is the right answer
so you see why TD tells me it's 7x
6 see whenever a occurred before B right
B is been very
unrewarding right only one out of the
three times B gave me a one but the
other times B occurred it had been very
rewarding twice it gave me a one and
once it gave me a
zero okay so what TD methods assume
implicitly is that the whole system is
Mark out so regardless of how I came to
be when I go out from B I'm going to get
that expected reward of
half right but it so happened that the
few samples I drew from a turned out to
be a bad sample for B right when I do
the monteal estimates I'm getting a
lower value for a because of that I
don't take into account the structure
right the structure is from a I go to B
and then I go to the terminal State and
what TD methods assume is okay from B if
you go to the terminal State this is the
reward you're going to get and therefore
from a if you go to B then you'll get
whatever reward you'll get from going
from B to the terminal say it makes that
very strong Mark of in
Assumption right and because it solves
for this Mark of chain okay so now let
me go back and ask you which is the
right
answer thank you yeah finally somebody
said it depends yeah depends on the
depends on the problem right it turns
out that what monara methods are doing
is essentially Trying to minimize the
prediction error right between
this particular set of samples that you
have drawn the returns computed
according to these samples alone right
going back to the definition of return
okay it is actually minimizing the
squared
error between
the value function you get and the the
return that you get from this right
you're just trying to minimize the
squared error from the fixed set of
samples that you
get right so what do TD methods do on
the other hand is they form what are
called certainty equivalence model okay
so people in control theory probably
understand this better so there is
something called the certainty
equivalence model which essentially is
the uh the model that best explains the
data that you have seen so far under
certain
assumptions okay so under certain
assumptions you can assume that this
model is equivalent to the system that
generated the data that you have seen so
far right in this case we are making a
very strong Markov assumption right and
what TD methods try to do is try to make
the prediction according to the
certainty equivalence model Trying to
minimize the error between the value
function in the certainty equivalence
model and the predictions you are making
here right so they are optimizing very
different objective
functions given an infinite amount of
data drawn from a truly maravian
system right both will converge to the
same
answer but given a finite amount of data
right this will converge to the
minimizer of the squared error this will
converge to whatever is the markco model
you can form with the limited data okay
this need not be the right model this
need not be the model that gave rise to
the data right given the limited data
this is the best you can do that's all
you can see we're saying here given this
data what is a model you can form it
will Converse to that right whether this
is the right answer or that is the right
answer given a limited amount of data
depends on what kind of application
you're looking at right on the other
hand since the Monaro methods make a
less of an assumption about maress if
you suspect that your system is not very
Marco Okay then don't use TD methods
you're better off probably better of
using mlo kind of methods okay but
remember I told you that if you use the
notion of a value function already
you're are making an assumption about
Mark of inness right otherwise you
should be using values of histories
right you shouldn't be using values of
States if you're already using of States
you are making a maravan assumption but
that's okay right in some sense provided
the reward estimates you are making
since then right you you take care of uh
the uh Mark awareness nonar awareness
there okay but still it's not correct
but at least it'll be more robust to
violations of the mark of assumptions
and as you can see very clearly from
here right just going by the evidence of
the trajectories I have given you you
should not think this is a mark of
system right so whenever a happens B
seems to have a depressed
outcome right just by the evidence of
the data here you shouldn't think it's a
mark of system but TD will just assume
it's a Marco system and go ahead and do
the updates
okay so you see the difference between
what TD does and what cor okay great so
we'll stop here we'll worry about TD
control the next class liit data MC will
converge to
MC will converts to the uh the least
Square
estimate of the returns predicted by the
data
[Applause]